<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CAREER: Hybrid Vapor Deposition Fabrication of Heterogeneous Biocidal Surfaces</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>437277</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate for Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division of Civil, Mechanical, and Manufacturing Innovation</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Alexis Lewis</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The research objective of this Faculty Early Career Development (CAREER) award is to establish the processing-structure-property interrelationships in heterogeneous biocidal surfaces. The biocidal surfaces are created using the vapor deposition of crosslinked and grafted polymers, which is a solvent-free, single-step method for the surface engineering of a wide variety of material and geometry. The research project will investigate the surface engineering with biocidal and biocompatible polymers distributed at different spatial scale and elucidate how process variables during the vapor deposition influence the surface structure. In addition, the bacteria adhesion, biofilm formation, antibacterial efficiency, and cell cytotoxicity will be studied to understand the interaction of the engineered surfaces with bacteria and mammalian cells. The research will also identify effective factors that determine the surface biocidal activity by correlating the results obtained from surface characterization, bacteria studies, and cell cytotoxicity studies of surfaces with both spatial and compositional heterogeneousness. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;If successful, the research will result in an environmentally benign and cost-effective method of creating non-leaching antibacterial surfaces. Example applications include self-sterilizing medical devices with reduced development of bacterial resistance and improved patient safety. The study on heterogeneous surfaces with biocidal and biocompatible components immobilized will significantly advance the understanding of biocidal surface design with both efficient bacteria killing and enhanced biocompatibility. In addition, the project will improve education and increase interest in biomaterials study through curriculum development and an educational website. The education plan will also boost participation of minority and women students in science, technology, engineering, and mathematics. The research results will be disseminated to industry to promote technological innovation in surface engineering.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/11/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/11/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1056074</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Yu</FirstName>
      <LastName>Mao</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>yu.mao@okstate.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/11/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Oklahoma State University</Name>
      <CityName>Stillwater</CityName>
      <ZipCode>740781011</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4057449995</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>101 WHITEHURST HALL</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Oklahoma</StateName>
      <StateCode>OK</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
